Guide to the Henri Peyre Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henri Peyre collection
1914-1988
MS 1395
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.25
The Henri M. Peyre Collection consists of a single volume presented to Professor Peyre on the occasion of his eightieth birthday. The volume contains photostatic copies of almost 350 letters from former Yale students, written in 1980 and 1981, with a foreword by Georges May.
Peyre, Henri, 1901-1988
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Carl Bandelin, 1984; Westport Public Library, 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research, with the exception of gradebooks in accession 2004-M-016, which will be closed until January 1, 2049.
Scope and Contents
The Henri M. Peyre Collection consists of a single volume presented to Professor Peyre on the occasion of his eightieth birthday. The volume contains photostatic copies of almost 350 letters from former Yale students, written in 1980 and 1981, with a foreword by Georges May.
The volume was donated to the Yale Library by Carl Bandelin on September 12, 1984.
Biographical / Historical
Henri Maurice Peyre was born in Paris, February 21, 1901. After coming to the United States in 1925, he served on the Yale University faculty for thirty-five years, including twenty-five years as chairman of the Department of French. Peyre died in December 1988.
Literature -- History and criticism; Educators; Festa-McCormick, Diana; Peyre, Henri, 1901-1988; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Dept. of French
- Inventory
  - Bound volume of letters from former Yale students, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional Material, 1914-1988; Accession 2004-M-016
  Scope and Contents
  Much of this accession is arranged as received. Whenever possible, original folder titles were used.
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - B-W (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Cohn, Robert (Bob), 1986 January-May (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Draper, Theodore (Ted), 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Garrell, Jacques, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Hertz, David, 1984, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Jameson, Fred, 1971 Mar, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Jeanneney, Jean-Marcel, 1965 November 14, 1966 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Lawler, Jim, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Macfarlane, Keith, 1975, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Matthews, John H., 1984, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Mickel, Emanuel, 1987 March 27, October 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Regalado, Antonio, 1984 February-March (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Sellin, Eric, 1983, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Stonehill Publishing [ Carrot Top! ], 1975, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Szogyi, Alex [includes story "Mother"], 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Family
      - McCormick, Carlo, 1980, 1982, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 16 - 17)
      - McCormick, Diana Festa, 1985 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - McCormick, Marco, 1975, 1979-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 19 - 25)
      - McCormick, Reiko, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 26 - 27)
      - McCormick, Sergio, 1981, 1988, 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 28 - 29)
      - Peyre, Henri, 1984 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Personal Papers
    - Certificates/degrees
      - Honorary Doctor of Letters degree from the State University of New York, 1984 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Membership certificate for the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1957 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Grade books, 1951-1973
    General note
    See: Accession 2004-M-016, 1914-1988 Box 3
  - Journal of menus and seating plans for dinners with family and friends, 1975-1988 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Lock of hair, money order receipt, course schedule for Marco McCormick, 1971 May 28, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Pen holder [inscribed Hommage au Professeur Henri Peyre, Le 20 Mars 1966, L'Union Saint Jean-Baptiste D'Amérique], 1966 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Spanish phrase book, handwritten, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Subject files
    - Athéisme, histoire des religions, esclavage, péché originel, 1962, 1976, 1982, 1984, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Barthes, Roland, 1953, 1960, 1967, 1970, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Bonald, Louis de, 1983, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Claudel, 1914, 1930, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Diderot, Denis, 1938, 1958-1959, 1968, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor, 1921, 1965, 1975-1978, 1980, 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Draper, Theodore, "The Idea of the 'Cold War' and Its Prophets", 1979 February (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Grossman, Kathryn, The Early Novels of Victor Hugo: Towards a Poetics of Harmony, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Haft, Cynthia, "The 'Thematic' Criticism of Jean-Paul Weber", 1974 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Humanities pedagogy, foreign language instruction, 1954, 1956, 1960, 1966, 1981, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Langlois, Walter, 1968, 1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Literary quotes, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Montégut, Emile, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Nietzsche, Friedrich, 1938, 1958, 1963, 1967, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Les Nouvelles de Balzac, 1962, 1966, 1978-1980, 1984, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - La Nuit dans les Nuits (One Thousand and One Nights), May, Georges, 1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Ozick, Cynthia, 1985, 1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Perse, Saint-John, 1947, 1948, 1952-1955, 1960-1964, 1967-1978, 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Picon, Gaëtan, D'Une Esthétique Contemporaine, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Progrès, Nature, 1977, 1978, 1980, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Riffaterre, Michael, 1959-1961, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Rousseau, Jean-Jacques, [1958?], 1965, 1973, 1974, 1983, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Russian poets and poetry, 1976, 1983, 1986, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Structuralisme: Claude Lévi-Strauss, 1974, 1976, 1978, 1981, 1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Szogyi, Alex, "Truth-Telling and Truth Suggesting in Molière's Theatre", 1971 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - U.S. novel, 1956, 1963, 1968, 1972 1976, 1981, 1985, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Valéry, Paul, 1927, 1929, 1931, 1937, 1942, 1945-1947, 1957-1964, 1971-1976, 1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 63 - 65)
    - Wellek, René, "Russian Formalism", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Miscellaneous notes, 1954, 1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Writings
    - Caws, Mary Ann, "Realizing Fictions", 1983 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - McCormick, Marco, short stories, 1983 May-Jun, 1986 Jun, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Peyre, Henri and Diana Festa McCormick, book reviews, 1947, 1965, 1966, 1985, 1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Unidentified poem, possibly by Sergio McCormick, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Photographs
    - Peyre, Henri, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - McCormick, Diana Festa and children, undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Unidentified,---, Gabrielle, 1966, 1968, 1970 Feb, 1971 Feb, undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Negatives, Mcormick, Hélène and Alex Szogyi, undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Gradebooks, 1951-1973 (Box 3)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 3 of Accession 2004-M-016 is closed until January 1, 2049 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.